Register of the Ryszard Wraga Papers, 1947-1959
Hoover Institution Archives
Ryszard Wraga Papers,
1947-1959
XX407
Wraga, Ryszard
6 manuscript boxes 2.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, memoranda, and other writings, relating to post-World War II politics in the Soviet Union and Poland, American and Soviet intelligence and propaganda activities, and activities of Russian and Ukrainian emigre groups. Many of the documents were prepared for the French intelligence service
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Espionage; Propaganda; Russians in foreign countries; Ukrainians in foreign countries; Poland; Poland--Politics and government--1945-1980; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Ukraine; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1945-1991
Biographical Note
1902, July 25 Born Jerzy Antoni Niezbrzycki in Niemirov, Ukraine Degree in law; graduate work in geography and philosophy, University of Warsaw
1927-1930 Polish diplomatic service, Moscow and Kiev
1931-1939 Director of Eastern Section of Polish military intelligence; member, faculty of Polish Military Academy and Institute of Journalism
1939-1945 Serves with Polish armed forces in Poland and the West
1945-1949 Resides in London; lectures at Polish Institute of Eastern Affairs and Free Polish University; becomes British subject and changes name to Ryszard Wraga
1949-1958 Resides in Paris; acts as consultant on Soviet Affairs to French Foreign Office Research Department
1958 Emigrates to the U.S.; works at Library of Congress
1963-1967 Research Associate at Hoover Institution, Stanford University
1968, January 30 Dies, Leesburg, Virginia
Series description
- Reports and Analyses. (Box 1-3)
  Handwritten reports in Russian by Ryszard Wraga re the internal situation and foreign policy of China, West Germany, Poland, the Ukraine, the U.S.S.R. and Yugoslavia. Also includes material on the Communist Party of the U.S.S.R. Arranged alphabetically by topic. 1951-1956.
- Post-War Anti-Soviet Emigre Organizations. (Box 3-4)
  Reports, minutes of meetings, press releases and correspondence of Russian, East European and Caucasian post-war anti-Soviet organizations. Includes materials of the American Committee of Struggle for the Freedom of Nations, 1' Institut pour l'etude de l'histoire et de la culture de l'U.R.S.S., L.B.N.S., N.T.S., R.A.O., S.B.O.N.R., S.O.N.R. and the Wiesbaden Conference. Arranged alphabetically by organization. 1949-1952.
- Journals and Printed Materials. (Box 4-5)
  Includes series of lectures in Polish on Russian and East European topics, Kurs Spraw Wschodnich, Institut Blieskiego i Srodkowego Wschodu "Reduta", London, 1949. Also includes Intermarium Biuletyn, Srodkowo Europejski Klub Federalny w Rzyme, Rome, 1947; Sprawy Bialoruskie, London, 1951; Sprawy Ukrainskie, London, 1950-1952; Szkola Nauk Politycznkych i Spolecznych, London, 1951; Wschod Polski, Institut Wschodni "Reduta", London, 1950-1952.
- Subject File (Box 5-6)
  Miscellaneous typescript reports, articles and documents re Poland, the Ukraine and the U.S.S.R. Arranged alphabetically by topic. 1918-1953.
Container List
- Handwritten Reports and Analyses
  - China
    - "Kooperatsia sel'skogo khoziaistva v Kitae i ego otzvuk v drugikh kommunisticheskikh stranakh", 1955 (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - "Le Huitieme Congres du P.C. Chinois", 1956 (Folder 2)
    - "Novaia konstitutsiia Kitaiskoi Narodnoi Respubliki" (Folder 3)
    - "Stat'ia Mao-Tse Toung: `Otnositel'no praktiki' " (Folder 4)
  - Germany, West
    - "Doklad o poezdke v Germaniiu (amerikanskaia i frantsuzskaia zona) v sentiabre 1950" (Folder 5)
    - "Zakliucheniia i vyvody" (Folder 6)
  - Poland
    - "Nekotorye dannyie otnosiashchiesia k kharakteristiki segodniashnei molodezhi v Pol'she" (Folder 7)
    - "Obshchee polozhenie v Pol'she" (Folder 8)
    - "Pol'skie kommunisty na Zapade" (Folder 9)
    - "Propagande anti-sovietique et anti-communiste destinee a la Pologne" (Folder 10)
    - " `Reabilitatsia' kommunisticheskikh partii Pol'shi i Vengrii" (Folder 11)
    - "Reorganizatsiia sluzhby gosudarstvennoi bezopastnosti v Pol'skoi Narodnoi Respubliki" (Folder 12)
    - "Rol', znachenie i vozmozhnosti Pol'shi v sluchae konflikta mezhdu U.S.S.R. i Zapadom" (Folder 13)
    - Untitled fragment (Folder 14-15)
  - Ukraine
    - Soviet Ukraine
      - "Polozhenie na Ukraine" (Folder 16)
      - "Predstoiashchii protses ukrainskikh natsionalistov v Varshave" (Folder 17)
      - "Prepodovanie istorii Frantsii na Ukraine" (Folder 18)
      - "Rech' Marshala V.I. Chuikova na XIX Sezde Partii Ukrainy" (Folder 19)
      - "XII Sezd kommunisticheskoi partii Ukrainy" (Folder 20)
    - Ukrainian emigration
      - "Asosiatsiia ukrainskikh nezavisimykh izsledovatelei sovetskoi teorii i praktiki v oblasti natsional'nykh problem" (Folder 21)
      - "Chetvertyii Sezd Ukrainskoi Demokraticheskoi Partii (U.R.D.P.)" (Folder 22)
      - "Otnoshenie ukrainskoi politicheskoi emigratsii k uchastiiu Ukr. Sov. Sots. Respubliki v O.N.U." (Folder 23)
      - "Ukrainskaia emigratsiia v Germanii" (Folder 24)
  - U.S.S.R.
    - Economics
      - "Analiz shestogo piatiletnego plana S.S.S.R." (Folder 25)
      - "Elementy k biudzhetu S.S.S.R. na 1952". Fragment (Folder 26)
      - "Nekotorye voprosy ekonomiki kolkhozov" (Folder 27)
      - "Organizatsiia upravleniia sovetskoi promyshlennosti" (Folder 28)
      - "Planirovanie i `detsentralizatsiia"' (Folder 29)
      - "Platezhesposobnyi spros i proizvodstvo v S.S.S.R." (Folder 30)
      - "Politichesko-strategicheskii kharakter industrializatsii Vostoka S.S.S.R." (Folder 31)
      - "Tiazholaia industriia v ekonomiki satelicheskikh stran" (Folder 32)
      - Untitled fragment (Folder 33)
    - Foreign policy
      - General
        - "Dvoistvennost' v sovetskoi politike i propagande mira" (Folder 34)
        - "Kommentarii k poslednim peremeshcheniiam v sovetskoi diplomatii" (Folder 35)
        - "Teoreticheskoe obosnovanie nekotorykh printsypov segodniashnei sovetskoi politiki" (Folder 36)
        - "Vozmozhnost' rezkogo izmeneniia general'noi linii stalinskoi vneshnei politiki" (Folder 37)
        - "Zamechaniia po povodu politiki i propagandy razoruzheniia" (Folder 38)
        - Untitled fragments (Folder 39)
      - China
        - "Edinnaia liniia sovetskoi i kitaiskoi propagandy" (Folder 40)
        - "Osobennosti sotsialisticheskogo preobrazovaniia Kitaia v osveshchenii sovetskoi propagandy" (Folder 41)
        - "Nekotorye osobennosti sovetsko-kitaiskikh otnoshenii" (Folder 42)
      - Colonialism
        - "Sovetskii analiz polozheniia v kolonial'nykh i zavisimykh stranakh i v chastnosti na Blizhnem i Srednem Vostoke". Fragment (Folder 43)
        - "Teoreticheskoe (doktrinal'noe) obosnovanie sovetskoi politiki po otnosheniiu k narodam Blizhnego i Srednego Vostoka" (Folder 44)
      - Socialist Republics
        - "Nekotorye osobennosti destalinizatsii v oblasti vzaimootnoshenii i ekonomiki stran Sovetskogo Bloka" (Folder 45)
        - "Sovetskaiia vneshniia politika v otsenke pol'skogo diplomata" (Folder 46)
        - "Vopros edinstva sotsialisticheskikh i kommunisticheskikh partii" (Folder 47)
    - History and historiography
      - "Novyi kurs sovetskoi istoriografii" (Box 2., Folder 1)
      - "Revizionizm roli Stalina v grazhdanskoi voine" (Folder 2)
      - "Rol' Lenina i Stalina v obrazovanii Sovetskogo Soiuza" (Folder 3)
      - "Stoletie so dnia rozhdeniia G.V. Plekhanova v S.S.S.R." (Folder 4)
      - "Uchastie S.S.S.R. i satelicheskikh stran v grazhdanskoi voine v Ispanii" (Folder 5)
      - "Voprosy periodizatsii istorii kom. partii S.S.S.R." (Folder 6)
      - "Vozstanovlenie roli Lenina kak voennogo deiatelia" (Folder 7)
      - "Vyderzhki iz raboty Lenina `La maladie infantile du communisme' " (Folder 8)
    - Ideology and theory of communism
      - "Dvatsatiletie sovetskoi konstitutsii i vopros `sotsialisticheskoi demokratii' " (Folder 9)
      - "Kharakteristika vtorogo izdaniia `Manuel d'economie politique' " (Folder 10)
      - "Kommentarii k statie D.Sheplova v Pravde 24.I s.g." (Folder 11)
      - "Nekotoryie izmeneniia v sovetskom tolkovanii `zakona krizisa kapitalisticheskoi sistemy' " (Folder 12)
      - "Nekotoryie voprosy kommunisticheskoi doktriny v S.S.S.R.' " (Folder 13)
      - "Osnovy segodniashnei sovetskoi natsional'noi politiki" (Folder 14)
      - "Opredelenie roli i znacheniia Stalina v sovremennoi teorii marksizma" (Folder 15)
      - " `Parlamentskie formy perekhoda k sotsializmu" (Folder 16)
      - "Partiinye trebovaniia v oblasti filosofii" (Folder 17)
      - " `Raspad kolonial'noi sistemy' v sovremennoi sovetskoi doktrine" (Folder 18)
      - "Revizionizm v oblasti istorii russkogo imperializma" (Folder 19)
      - "Rol'i mesto natsional'nogo voprosa v doktrine stalinizma" (Folder 20)
      - "Sovetskaia filosofskaia literatura posle-stalinovskogo perioda kak istochnik poznaniia sovetskoi deistvitel'nosti i kliuch k ponimaniiu sovetskoi politiki" (Folder 21)
      - "Sovremennoe ponimanie `dialekticheskogo materializma' v S.S.S.R." (Folder 22)
      - "Teoriia integratsii mirovoi sotsialisticheskoi sistemy" (Folder 23)
      - "Vnutrennie ideologicheskie protivorechiia v Sovetskom Soiuze" (Folder 24)
      - "Vopros edinstva `sotsialisticheskoi sistemy' " (Folder 25)
      - "Voprosy leninizma-stalinizma v aktual'noi sovetskoi politiki" (Folder 26)
      - "Voprosy `sotsialisticheskogo obshchestva' v sovetskoi teoreticheskoi literature" (Folder 27)
      - Untitled fragments (Folder 28)
    - Internal affairs
      - "Diskusiia po voprosam sudebnogo upravleniia v S.S.S.R." (Folder 29)
      - "Dvatsatiletie Sovetskoi Konstitutsii i vozmozhnosti ee izmeneniia" (Folder 30)
      - "Nekotorye voprosy kollektivnogo rukavodstva v S.S.S.R." (Folder 31)
      - "Nekotorye voprosy predstoiashchei reorganizatsii sovetskoi militsii" (Folder 32)
      - "Otritsatel'nyia iavleniia v zhizni sovetskoi molodezhi" (Folder 33)
      - "Otstavka ministra vnutrennikh del S.S.S.R.- S.N. Kruglova" (Folder 34)
      - "Politicheskaia programma Kommun. Partii Sovetskogo Soiuza v sviazi s vyborami v Verkhovnyie Sovety soiuznykh i avtonomnykh respublik" (Folder 35)
      - "Postanovka vyborov v mestnye sovety" (Folder 36)
      - "Protivorechie i konflikty vo vnutrennem polozhenii S.S.S.R." (Folder 37)
      - "Stat'ia B.I. Nikolaevskogo" (Folder 38)
      - Untitled fragment (Folder 39)
    - Military
      - "Marksistskaia doktrinal'naia baza novoi sovetskoi voennoi doktriny" (Folder 40)
      - "Nekotorye osobennosti voennogo biudzheta S.S.S.R." (Folder 41)
      - "Opyt kharakteristiki sovetskoi voennoi doktriny" (Folder 42)
      - "Osnovnye elementy sovetskoi diskusii po povodu voennoi doktriny" (Folder 43)
      - "Otnoshenie partii k Sovetskoi Armii" (Folder 44)
      - "Vooruzhennykh sil organicheskii s soboiu Sviazany i neotdelimy" (Folder 45)
      - Untitled fragments. Commentaries on two articles in Posev, 1952 (Folder 46)
    - Propaganda
      - "Aktivnost' `fabrikantov informatsii' po voprosam sviazannym s atomnym vooruzheniem S.S.S.R." (Box 3., Folder 1)
      - "Arabskii vopros v sovetskoi propagande" (Folder 2)
      - "Intensification de l'effort bolsheviste en France" (Folder 3)
      - "Nekotorye osobennosti amerikanskoi politicheskoi i voennoi informatsii i razvedki a takzhe sovetskoi desinformatsii i inspiratsii" (Folder 4)
      - "Nekotorye osobennosti segodniashnei ofitsial'noi sovetskoi propagandy" (Folder 5)
      - "Quelques particularites de la propagande sovietique d'aujourd'hui"
      - "Voprosy raschleneniia Rossii v segodniashnei sovetskoi propagande" (Folder 6)
      - Untitled fragments (Folder 7)
  - Communist Party of the U.S.S.R.
    - General
      - "Analiz 'Prizyvov TSentral'nogo Komiteta Kom. Partii S.S.S.R.' k 38-oi godovshchine oktiabrskoi revoliutsii" (Folder 8)
      - "Bor'ba s 'liberal'nymi metodami' " (Folder 9)
      - "Bor'ba za ideinuiu ubezhdennost' vnutri K.P.S.S." (Folder 10)
      - "Nekotorye kommentarii k dokladu L.M.Kaganovicha na partiinom zasidanii Moskovskogo Soveta v noiabre 1955" (Folder 11)
      - "Nekotorye otritsatel'nye iavleniia vnutri Kom. Partii S.S.S.R." (Folder 12)
      - "Novaiia chistka partii" (Folder 13)
      - "Osnovnye problemy komsomola i vliianie na nego sobytii v satelicheskikh stran" (Folder 14)
      - "Personal'nyi uklad novykh rukovodiashchikh organov Kommunisticheskoi Partii Sovetskogo Soiuza" (Folder 15)
      - "Predstoiashchie peremeshcheniia v rukovodstve V.K.P. i v pravitel'stve S.S.S.R." 1951 (Folder 16)
      - "Raspredelenie chlenov i kandidatov TS.K. partii po partiinym i gosudarstvennym organam S.S.S.R." (Folder 17)
      - "Stat'ia v 'Pravda' ot 8.vi. s.g." (Folder 18)
    - XIX Party Congress
      - "Analiz teksta izmennenago Ustava partii, predstavlennago v vide proekta TSentral'nago Komiteta V.K.P.(b) dlia utverzhdeniia na XIX Sezde Partii" (Folder 19)
      - "Znachenie sozyva XIX Congress of the C.P.S.U.(B) i predstoiashchei reorganizatsii partii s tochki zreniia sovetskoi vneshnei i revoliutsionnoi politiki" (Folder 20)
      - "Nekotorye zamechaniia po povodu XIX S'ezda partii" (Folder 21)
      - Untitled fragment (Folder 22)
    - XX Party Congress
      - "Analiz vyborov v verkhovnye organy partii na XX S'ezde P.C.U.S." (Folder 23)
      - "Analiz XX Sezda Kommunisticheskoi Partii Sovetskogo Soiuza (14-25 fevralia 1956 goda)". Fragments of draft (Folder 24)
      - "Elementy dlia programmy kom. partii Sovetskogo Soiuza k XX Sezdu" (Folder 25)
      - "Nekotorye osobennosti protsesa destalinizatsii v svete t. naz. 'Tainogo Doklada Khrushcheva'i resoliutsii TSentr. Komiteta Kom. Partii S.S.S.R. ot 30.vi.1956 g." (Folder 26)
      - "Opredelenie roli kommunisticheskoi partii Sovetskogo Soiuza kak odna iz zadach sovetskoi i kommunisticheskoi propagandy pered XX S'ezdom partii" (Folder 27)
      - "Rapport d'activite du Comite Central du Partie Communiste de l'Union Sovietique au XX Congres du Partie" (Folder 28)
      - " 'Tainyi doklad' Khrushcheva na XX Sezde P.S.C.U." (Folder 29)
      - "Vystuplenie na sezde chlenov presidiuma i sekretariata TS. K. Partii du P.C.S.U." (Folder 30)
      - Untitled fragment (Folder 31)
  - Yugoslavia
    - "Protivorechiia mezhdu doktrinoi Iugoslavii i leninismom" (Folder 32)
    - "Statiia Marshala Iosip Broz-Tito v sovetskom zhurnale 'Kommunist' " (Folder 33)
    - "Taktika kominforma" (Folder 34)
    - Untitled fragment (Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Liberalism" (Folder 36)
    - "O mladorosskoi ideologii" (Folder 37)
    - "Russkie sotsial-demokraty (mensheviki) o peremenakh v sovetskom pravitel'stve" (Folder 38)
- Post-War Anti-Soviet Emigre Organizations
  - General
    - "Amerikanische Versuche zur Schaffung einer russischen Einheitsfront", 1950 (Box 3., Folder 39)
    - "Freiheitsbund fur Deutsch Russische Freundschaft" (Folder 40)
    - "Grosse antibolschewistishe Action", 1950 (Folder 41)
    - "The Problem of a United or Divided Russia" (Folder 42)
    - "Rezoliiutsiia mitinga predstavitelei rossiiskoi emigratsii", Munchen, 1951 (Folder 43)
    - "Sytuacja polityczna emigracji rosyjskiej w 1951 roku" (Folder 44)
    - "Vorbereitung des Kongresses 'Freies Russland' " (Folder 45)
    - Wraga, Ryszard, handwritten report re Russian emigration (Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous handwritten reports (Folder 47)
  - American Committee of Struggle for the Freedom of Nations; handwritten reports by Ryszard Wraga (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Institute for the Study of the U.S.S.R., Eleventh Conference; Wraga, Ryszard, "Basic Problems of Soviet Foreign Policy, Methods and Means", Munich, 1959 (Folder 2)
  - Institut pour l'etude de l'histoire et de la culture de l'U.R.S.S., (Munchen); handwritten reports by Ryszard Wraga (Folder 3)
  - L.B.N.S. (Liga Bor'by za Narodnuiu Svobodu) (Folder 4)
    - Dallin, D., "Pochemu ia ushel", Novoe Russkoe Slovo, Sept. 30, 1951
    - Open letter, anonymous
  - "Monde Nouveau"; handwritten reports by Ryszard Wraga (Folder 5)
  - N.T.S. (Natsional'nyi Trudovoi Soiuz) (Folder 6)
    - Letter to the Editor of the New York Times, Apr. 29, 1951
    - Handwritten reports by Ryszard Wraga (Folder 7)
  - R.A.O. (Rossiiskoe Antikommunisticheskoe Ob'edinenie); "Spravka o Rossiiskom Antikommunisticheskom Ob'edinenii (R.A.O.)", 1950 (Folder 8)
  - "Return to the Motherland"; handwritten reports by Ryszard Wraga (Folder 9)
  - S.B.O.N.R. (Soyuz Bor'by za Osvobozhdenie Narodov Rossii)
    - Conference, May, 1952. Financial report, schedule of activities (Folder 10)
    - Declaration, 1951 (Folder 11)
    - Iakovlev, B., correspondence, 1951 (Folder 12)
    - International Conference, Wiesbaden, excerpts from Protocol No. 1, 1951 (Folder 13)
    - "Osnovnoi dokument no. 1" (Folder 14)
    - Reports, no. 1-3, 5, 1952 (Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous materials, 1950-1951 (Folder 16)
  - S.O.N.R. (Sovet Osvobozhdeniia Narodov Rossii)
    - Dikov, Iu.V., letter calling for cooperation among emigre organizatins (Folder 17)
    - Information Bulletins of the Press Bureau, no. 5-9, 11, 1951 (Folder 18)
    - Protocols of meetings, no. 10, 12, 14-16, 18, 1951 (Folder 19)
    - Reports re activities and projected activities, no. 1-2, 4-6, 8-10, 1951 (Folder 20)
    - Resolutions re the establishment of S.O.N.R., document no. 2, 3 (Folder 21)
    - Handwritten reports by Ryszard Wraga (Folder 22)
  - U.N.R. (Ukrainskaia Narodnaia Rada); motion of conference, March 4, 1951 (Folder 23)
  - Wiesbaden Conference, 1951
    - Declaration (Folder 24)
    - Protocols no. 1-2, 5-8 (Folder 25)
- Journals and Printed Matter
  - Intermarium, The Central European Federal Club, Rome, 1947, Biuletyn Nr.6 (Box 4., Folder 26)
  - Kurs Spraw Wschodnich, Institut Blieskiego i Srodkowego Wschodu "Reduta", London, 1949. (Series of printed lectures on East European and Russian subjects)
    - Series I, No. 2,3,5,7 (Folder 27)
    - Series II, No. 1,3,4,5,7,8,10 (Folder 28)
    - Series III, No. 1,2,4,5,7,8 (Folder 29)
    - Series IV, No. 1,2,3 (Folder 30)
  - Sprawy Bialoruskie, London, 1951 (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Sprawy Ukrainskie, London
    - 1950, No. 2-6, 14,16 (Folder 2)
    - 1951, No. 17-23,26, 28-36 (Folder 3)
    - 1952, No. 37-40, 42,44,45 (Folder 4)
  - Szkola Nauk Politycznych i Spolecznych, London, 1951 (Folder 5)
  - Wschod Polski, Institut Wschodni "Reduta", London
    - R.O.K. 1949-1950, No. 3-6 (Folder 6)
    - R.O.K. 1950-1951, No. 9,10,13 (Folder 7)
    - R.O.K. 1951-1952, No. 16 (Folder 8)
    - R.O.K. 1952-1953, No. 20-21 (Folder 9)
- Subject File
  - Poland
    - "Zasadnicze cechy projektu novej konstitucji polskiej", 1952 (Box 5., Folder 10)
    - List of members of the Polish government (Folder 11)
  - Polish emigration
    - "Instrukcja w sprawie przymusu pracy", 1943 (Folder 12)
      (Documents of the Vichy Government re foreign workers in France)
    - "L'existence des refugies polonais en Hongrie" (Folder 13)
    - "Polonica we Francji" (Folder 14)
    - "Repariacja Polakow z Rosji" (Folder 15)
    - Excerpts from criticism of pre-war Poland by Bertrand de Jouvenal and Loucien Bourgues (Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous material re A.B.N., 1951 (Folder 17)
  - Ukrainian emigration
    - "Emigracja ukrainska w czasie II wojny swiatowej" (Folder 18)
    - "Emigration ukrainienne et ses pourparles avec les Socialistes" (Folder 19)
    - "Le probleme ukrainien et l'emigration ukrainienne" (Folder 20)
    - Szandruk, Paul, excerpts from his article "Potentiel militaire de l'Ukraine", published in Svoboda, U.S.A., Nov. 1949 (Folder 21)
    - Wraga, Ryszard, commentary on article by "Porai" published in Ukrainskii Samostiinik, No. 47, Dec.3, 1950 (Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous material re anti-Soviet organizations (Folder 23)
  - U.S.S.R.
    - General
      - Bureau d'Information Russe, "Une delegation Socialiste Russe a Paris", Nov. 23, 1918 (Folder 24)
      - Confidential Security Information, "The Current Soviet Political Situation", Jan. 24, 1953 (Folder 25)
      - "Kak pishut istoriu v Sovetskom Soiuze" (Folder 26)
      - Koch, Hans, "Kirchliche Wandlungen in osteuropaischen Raum" (Folder 27)
      - "Pis'mo moskovskogo studenta", published in Forum, (organ of the Kongress Zashchity Kultury) (Folder 28)
      - "Probleme du peuple et du pouvoir en U.S.S.R." (Folder 29)
    - Communist Party of the U.S.S.R.
      - "Comite Central du P.C. de l'U.R.S.S. elu par le XX Congres de ce parti" (Box 6., Folder 1)
      - "Commentaires sur le XIX Congres du P.C. de l'Union Sovietique" (Folder 2)
      - "Composition (Annote) de la Commission Centrale de Controle du P.C. de l'U.R.S.S. elue par le XX Congres de ce parti" (Folder 3)
      - "Composition du Comite Centrale du P.C. de l'Union Sovietique" (Folder 4)
      - "La nouvelle epuration du parti" (Folder 5)
      - "L'U.R.S.S., les nouveaux organismes de direction du Parti Communiste de l'Union Sovietique" (Folder 6)
      - "U.R.S.S. Telegramme d'information", March 8, 1950 (Folder 7)
    - Economics
      - "A.S. du budget militaire de l'U.R.S.S. pour 1952" (Folder 8)
      - "A.S. du budget Sovietique" (Folder 9)
      - "Nouvelle campagne contre la paysannerie en U.R.S.S." (Folder 10)
      - "Particularites du budget militaire de l'U.R.S.S." (Folder 11)
      - "Quelques elements pour l'appreciation du budget de l'U.R.S.S. pour 1952" (Folder 12)
    - Foreign policy
      - "A.S. de l'offensive Sovietique de la paix" (Folder 13)
      - "Aspect ideologique et doctrinal du conflit Kremlin Tito" (Folder 14)
      - "La politique Sovietique dans le conflit avec Tito" (Folder 15)
      - "Les visees de la politique Sovietique au tournant de 1949-1950" (Folder 16)
      - "Possibilite d'un changement brusque de la ligne general de la politique exterieure stalinienne" (Folder 17)
      - Souvarine, Boris, "Offensive de Guerre Froide"" (Folder 18)